<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at White-hall on Sunday, the 17th of February, 169 4/5 before the right honourable the lord chamberlain, ladies of the bedchambers, and others of the houshold to our late gracious Queen Mary, of blessed memory / by J. Adams ...</title>
            <author>Adams, John, 1662-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32693</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12746365</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12746365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93258</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26336)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93258)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1028:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at White-hall on Sunday, the 17th of February, 169 4/5 before the right honourable the lord chamberlain, ladies of the bedchambers, and others of the houshold to our late gracious Queen Mary, of blessed memory / by J. Adams ...</title>
                  <author>Adams, John, 1662-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benj. Motts,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publish'd at the request of that honourable audience."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93258:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>WHITE-HALL,</hi> ON <hi>Sunday,</hi> the 17th. of <hi>February,</hi> 1694/5. Before the Right Honourable the Lord Chamberlain, Ladies of the Bed-Chamber, and others of the Houſhold to our late Gracious Queen <hi>MARY,</hi> of Bleſſed Memory.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. Adams,</hi> A. M. Rector of S. <hi>Alban's Woodſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd at the Requeſt of that Honourable Audience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by BENJ. MOTTE, 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:93258:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93258:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON ISAIAH xxxii. 17. <hi>The Work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Peace, and the Effect of Righteouſneſs Quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Aſſurance for Ever.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HUman Nature is very ſubject to Preſumption or Deſpair, according as mens Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are: this appears in the <hi>Jews</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly; and therefore 'twas the manner of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to mingle Threats and Promiſes together.</p>
            <p>Thus in the beginning of this Chapter, the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Prophet deſcribes our Saviour, and the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Kingdom, under the Perſon of <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah.</hi> (verſe 9.) Then turns them of a ſudden to a ſight of thoſe Miſeries which ſhould befal their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93258:3"/>before this ſhould come to paſs; but then leſt this ſhould deject them too much, he aſſures them that their Afflictions ſhall laſt no longer, then <hi>Until the Spirit was poured out upon them from on High,</hi> (verſe 15.) at which time <hi>Judgment ſhould dwell in the Wilderneſs, and Righteouſneſs remain in the fruitful Field.</hi> Nor was this all, but <hi>The Work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Peace, and the Effect of Righteouſneſs Quietneſs, and Aſſurance for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Work of Righteouſneſs is meant, as this place refers to Chriſt, and concerns us in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, the Acting according to the Precepts of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The Word Peace has a large ſignification, but ſeems to be uſed here for the inward Peace or Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of the Soul: By Quietneſs is meant Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from outward Dangers: by Aſſurance for Ever a Settled Truſt, an Entire Confidence in God.</p>
            <p>That the Work of Righteouſneſs produces Peace, Quietneſs, and Aſſurance for Ever, in theſe Senſes which I have mention'd, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">I. As to the Inward Peace, or Tranquility of the Soul; the Work of Righteouſneſs caules this upon ſeveral accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93258:3"/> 1. Becauſe this is moſt Natural to the Soul of Man. If Reaſon be the thing which diſtinguiſhes Man from other Creatures, his Eaſe and Happineſs muſt conſiſt in the Acting according to this, and the improvement of it. But Reaſon leads us of it ſelf to the chief grounds of thoſe things which are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us in the Goſpel, as the Works of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: as the Knowledge of a God, of Good and Evil, and Reward and Puniſhment hereafter.</p>
            <p>And tho men are ſometimes ſo perverſe, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to deſtroy theſe Notions in themſelves and others, yet all the while they do this Violence to their Underſtandings, the Soul is unnaturally forc'd and ſtrain'd, as appears by its frequent ſtriving in Doubts and Fears. Whereas he that Acts according to his Reaſon, and Endeavours to improve the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Notions of a God by Searching into His Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd Will, and living according to it, does that which is moſt agreeable to His Nature, and finds the moſt perfect Peace of Mind; and the Reſt and Acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcence, which is the Effect of having done Well, is like that which Natural Bodies find by lying ſtill in their proper Places: Which proves that Righteouſneſs is particularly agreeable to the Soul of Man, and that the Works of it give Peace and Satisfaction; while every Work of Wickedneſs is Acting contrary to ſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93258:4"/>Principle or other belonging to it, and conſequently cauſes Diſquiet and Confuſion.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Work of Righteouſneſs, or the Acting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Precepts of the Goſpel, brings Peace to the Mind, by leading it to a clearer Knowledge of God than it can have from Nature, and by conducing to the improvement of that Knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho the corruptible body preſſeth down the Soul, and the earthly tabernacle weighteth down the mind. Wiſd.</hi> 9.15. yet theſe Expreſſions ſhew that this is unnatural, and argue Reſiſtance and Reluctancy; Accordingly, we may obſerve that the Soul is frequently ſtrugling and endeavouring upwards, and by its quitting ſo ſoon its fulleſt Enjoyments, by its perpetually hunting about after new Objects, ſhews plainly, that Nothing of this World is of ſufficient Worth, to improve, or employ it. But if at length it can, by the Aſſiſtance of Right Reaſon and Divine Grace, raiſe itſelf to Heaven, what Joy, what ſweet Acquieſcence does it find in the Knowledg and Contemplation of its God! For if there be the ſtrongeſt Inclination to Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween things of the ſame Nature, the Soul being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>material, can have no immediate, no proper Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion with material Objects; But when it meets with Spiritual ones, rejoyces in what is like itſelf: How then muſt it be pleaſed, when it has diſcovered
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93258:4"/>the Father of Spirits! What unſpeakable Joy muſt it find, in being united to God himſelf by the Works of Righteouſneſs!</p>
            <p>But alas! In how wretched a Condition was Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in this Regard before the Goſpel? How little Knowledge had they of God, and therefore how little Progreſs did they make in the Works of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue? Some thought Him a Cruel and Inflexible Being, and that whatever came to paſs, was by abſolute Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity; and this took off all Hope and Comfort in Affliction: Others thought Him an Idle and Careleſs Being, not concerning Himſelf at all with the Events of Things, or Actions of Men; and this took away the Reliſh of Succeſs, made it always ſuſpected, ſince what came by Chance, might be as quickly loſt by it. As for the Jews, tho they had a better Notion of the True God, yet the Paſſion which work'd chiefly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them was Fear: God revealed Himſelf to this ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born People, by His dreadful Attributes of Power and Juſtice, and therefore their Obedience was Servile and Uneaſie to 'em: But how ſoon were all theſe Evils Remedy'd! And how plainly did God Reveal Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the whole World, by the Coming of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour? By His Coming the Abominations of the Heathen Worſhip, the Deluſions of their Oracles, the vain Boaſts of their Virtue were Diſcover'd, by the Coming of the <hi>Deſire of</hi> all <hi>Nations,</hi> the <hi>Prince of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93258:5"/>Peace,</hi> the <hi>Lord of Life and Glory:</hi> That Fear and Dread which attended the Moſaical Law was quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd by that Love which is the Foundation of the Goſpel; and the terrible Name of the <hi>Lord of Hoſts, the God to whom Vengeance belongeth,</hi> changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Mild and Sweet Style of <hi>the God of Peace and Conſolation, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> So that all here contributes to our inward Peace: Here Power and Goodneſs, Juſtice and Mercy, Moderate our Fear and Love ſo ſweetly, that they produce ſuch a Smoothneſs in the Mind, as cannot be equall'd by Love or Joy alone; for tho the Paſſions of Love and Joy are more agreeable to Nature, becauſe their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are what we ſuppoſe to be good, then Fear or Sadneſs, becauſe their Objects are what we ſuppoſe to be Evil; yet they are no leſs Troubleſome and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous in the Exceſs; So that they require a convenient Allay, and an equal Mixture of both together: and in this equal Mixture, wherein the Soul is neither toſs'd nor driven violently one way or other, conſiſts its Eaſe and Happineſs.</p>
            <p>This is that Eaſe which the Mind finds in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, which muſt be ſuppos'd as the Ground of our Obedience in Working Righteouſneſs; and this Knowledg is wonderfully increaſed by the Works of Righteouſneſs. A Barren Contemplation of the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Divine Nature, is no Improvement of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93258:5"/>Soul; but when it is withal fruitful in good Works, this is what the Scripture calls <hi>Drawing nearer to God,</hi> and being <hi>like Him:</hi> and for this God has promiſed His Holy Spirit; by which they ſhall have a more full Knowledg of Him. Thus our Bleſſed Saviour, (14. <hi>John</hi> 21. <hi>verſe.</hi>) <hi>He that hath my commandments, he it is that loveth me, and he that loveth me, ſhall be loved of my father, and I will love him, and will manifeſt my ſelf unto Him.</hi> And from theſe Grounds it is, that the Work of Righteouſneſs brings Peace to the Soul in the following Reſpects: as,</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Work of Righteouſneſs contributes to the Peace of the Soul, by the Pleaſure which is to be found in the inſtant of doing it. This, I do not queſtion, but every Body here has frequently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd: there is no one Work of Righteouſneſs which regards God or our Neighbour, but bring along with it its peculiar Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>What an unſpeakable Peace of Mind accompanies Devout and Fervent Prayer? How is the Heart en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged in Holy Joy, when it pours out itſelf in Praiſe and Thankſgiving to its Great and Good Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour? And when we aſſiſt our Neighbour, either by Relieving his Wants, or Comforting his Sorrows, are we not good to our ſelves, in the Satisfaction which we feel immediately, as well as the Reward which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93258:6"/>we expect hereafter! What a generous Delight is there in a Quick and Ample Return of any Benefit! And what a Bleſſing to a great Mind is the very Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of being grateful! But in that Nobleſt way of Conqueſt, of overcoming an Enemy with Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when 'tis in our Power to be Severe to him, is a more Rational and Complete Satisfaction, than in that which is counted by ſome the Sweeteſt of all things; Revenge. In a word, the moſt Solid, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime, and Durable Delight accompanies the Act of Doing Well; and tho there be much Danger in moſt kinds of Satisfaction in ones ſelf, there is no fear of Flattery in the Applauſe of a Faithful Conſcience. When a Soul well practis'd and experienc'd in Virtue, and conſcious of a due and regular Uſe of its free Will Acquieſces in its good Actions, and ſomething whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers from within, <hi>Well done thou good and faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.—Happy is the people that are in ſuch a caſe: yea, bleſſed is the man who has</hi> (thus) <hi>the Lord for his God. Pſal.</hi> 144. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The Work of Righteouſneſs promotes our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Peace by Regulating our Paſſions: How great Diſturbers of the Mind theſe are, is too well Known; and yet how ready is every Body to be led away by them: How little of the leaſt of them, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to make vain Man! That Lord of the World! That Boaſter of his Reaſon! A Tyrant over his fellow
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93258:6"/>Creatures, and a Slave to himſelf. Sometimes the uneaſineſs of Pride Sours him into Habitual Peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſometimes he is rais'd in unreaſonable Joy; and then caſt down again in as unjuſt Deſpair; then Envy and Ambition, Grief, Hatred, and Revenge, Rage in him by Turns, and often all together: What can expreſs the miſery of the Soul in this Condition? Yet this is not all; this makes a Man not only miſerable as to himſelf, but odious or Contemptible to all the World.</p>
            <p>There is ſomething in Gentleneſs and Meekneſs which is moſt proper to procure Reſpect and Love; For theſe Qualities are the Cauſes of Order and Beauty, not only in Peoples Looks, but in their Words and Actions; but in Anger or any other violent Paſſion, all is Deformity; yet ſuch a Deformity as becomes rather ridiculous than terrible; for tho it may ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe at firſt, yet when it is found to be unreaſonable and cuſtomary, it is ſcorn'd and contemn'd, and when it finds that it is ſo, it rages often unto Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Now this Violence of Paſſion is chiefly occaſion'd by Mens being miſtaken in their Eſteem or Diſlike of the things of this World, and the Raſhneſs of their Inclinations or Averſions accordingly. Whereas the Work of Righteouſneſs ſuppoſes a true Knowledg
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93258:7"/>of the Good and Evil of ſuch things; and is nothing elſe but a Regular Purſuit of the firſt, and an Orderly Flight from the latter: And in this conſiſts the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of all our Paſſions, and our Peace and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. An ill Man can find nothing of this, while his Paſſions drag or hurry him each a different way; But O, what Reſt, what Quiet, what Security of Mind can a good Chriſtian want, when every Work of Righteouſneſs joyns kindly with the other, and all contribute ſweetly to his Peace! The Wicked are, in reference to their Extravagant Reſtleſs Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>compar'd to a troubled ſea, which caſts up mire and dirt,</hi> (<hi>Iſ.</hi> 57.20.) Turn the Metaphor, and you will find the whole Life of the Righteous Man a continu'd Calm; How Compos'd is his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per! How moderate are his Deſires! and how well Govern'd his Fears!</p>
            <p>And this is not only caus'd but alſo promoted by ſuch Works of Righteouſneſs as are enjoyn'd by the Goſpel; becauſe that Jeſus who enjoyns them there, give us alſo the greateſt Example of Humility and Meekneſs: for with what Patience did He go about do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Good! Healing the Sick Graciouſly, Inſtructing the Ignorant Gently, and Reproving the Wicked Calmly! With what Lowlineſs did He bear the greateſt Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Contempt or Violence! Alas, if we reflect in the leaſt upon His miſerable Life and Death, we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93258:7"/>ſhall find a Thouſand Inſtances, wherein we may <hi>Learn of him to be meek and lowly,</hi> (<hi>Mat.</hi> 11.) and in ſo doing, to <hi>find Reſt to our Souls.</hi> When I name the Word Jeſus, ſays one of the Fathers, (<hi>Bernard. in</hi> 15. <hi>Serm. Cantic.</hi>) all that is Sweet and Delightful comes into my Mind; Grace, Mercy, Bounty, Forgiveneſs, Goodneſs and Love, compoſe the Bleſſed Sound, and the very Pronouncing of it, as it caſt out Devils heretofore, might be ſufficient now to Allay our Paſſions, and Compoſe our fierceſt Anger or Revenge.</p>
            <p>But of all the Paſſions, there is none more uneaſie than Fear, and no Object ſo apt to cauſe this as Death; but the Work of Righteouſneſs continues Peace to the Soul, by ſecuring it from this: The Wicked are in this Regard the fartheſt from any Peace, they own that Death cannot be avoided, they are ignorant when it will happen, and yet never think of it till 'tis upon 'em: Then all the Faculties of the Soul are in as great Confuſion as a Town taken by Surpriſe, and the ſtubborn obſtinate Wretch ſits him down, and expects the Worſt in a ſurly Deſpair: the more timorous ſneak and cringe in Officious Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; this upon a ſudden Attack of Death; but if it comes on by Degrees, if they reach old Age, what ſad Spectacles of Woe are they! What Ruines of Vice appear in every Limb! yet their greateſt Hell
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93258:8"/>is not viſible, the Torments of the Mind are far more inſupportable.</p>
            <p>But the Righteous feel nothing of all this; there can be no Fear where no Guilt is, and for Death it ſelf, they know that this is but the Paſſage to that Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which is their Reward: How bleſs'd and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py is he! How ſecure his Innocence! Who reflecting upon one well-ſpent Day, can ſay, <hi>Return to thy Reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord hath rewarded thee:</hi> 'Tis but doing thus for a little while, and he may with as much Readineſs and Joy lie down in the Grave.</p>
            <p>The Life of a Good Chriſtian ought to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Contemplation upon Death; for he that keeps this fartheſt Point in his Eye, ſhall never miſtake his Way: He that conſiders how ſoon his Body, tho <hi>it be fearfully and wonderfully made;</hi> though he be never ſo Healthful or ſo Young, ſo Great or ſo Good; is by the leaſt Accident ſhaken into its Duſt, will ever be in readineſs; if Death come never ſo unexpected, 'twill find him doing his Lords Will: but if he be continu'd to a good old Age, his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fails Regularly, becauſe he liv'd ſo; every Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Appetite grows leſs imperious, as every Senſe decays, and the Soul grows more ſprightly and vigorous the nearer it is to its Separation. Nay
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93258:8"/>let us follow ſuch a one to his laſt Minute, let us conſider him as juſt paſſing into the next World; if he have leiſure to look back on this, what a Bleſſed and Chearful Proſpect does his well ſpent Life afford him; how do his Works of Righteouſneſs riſe to his View in Numerous and Goodly Order! There where he ſees how many Naked he has Clothed, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sick he has Viſited, how many Temptations he has Mortified, has he any thing to do think you but to Comfort his Friends uſeleſs and unreaſonable Sorrow? Or does any Paſſion move him, unleſs it be a Holy Joy for the Nearneſs of Eternity? No, certainly, <hi>Mark the perfect, and behold the upright;</hi> for whatever his Life is, 'tis certain that the Death, <hi>the end of that man is Peace. Pſal.</hi> 37.37.</p>
            <p>But it may be objected, that a Man may be ſo abſolute an Atheiſt, and have ſo ſear'd a Conſcience, as to be paſt feeling, paſt any Senſe of Guilt, or Fear of Death; ſuch a Monſter can ſcarce be fancied, but never known: the moſt Speculative Atheiſt can get no farther than Incertainty as to a God and future State, and how far incertainty in a matter of ſo great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance can contribute to a ſettled Peace of Mind, any one may gueſs, when what Pains ſoever he ſhall take to Root up or Stifle theſe Notions, the Danger, the diſmal Conſequence of being miſtaken, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn often upon him, and let him chooſe what
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93258:9"/>Vice he pleaſes (for that's the modern way of Diſpelling theſe Vapours, as they call 'em) yet after the moſt induſtrious Debauch, this Qualm of Mind will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways follow; but more eſpecially if any Calamity befalls him, what a Wretch does he grow without Council or Courage; then however he has been entranc'd for a Moment, the frightful Images of his former Wickedneſs return more powerfully, and increaſing ſtill in Terrour as Death draws on: <hi>There is no Peace, ſaith my God, unto the Wicked; the way of Peace they have not known</hi> in their Lives, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall never find it at their Deaths.</p>
            <p n="5">V. The Work of Righteouſneſs does not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Peace in the Act of doing Well, but alſo by the memory of ſuch Actions; by leaving ſuch ſweet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon the Soul, as bleſs us as often as we Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon them with ever new and everlaſting, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. What Horrour! Confuſion and Dejection of Soul attends the Reflections of an ill Conſcience! When a Wretch conſiders how Perverſly, and Ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully he has neglected, or Deſpis'd the moſt gentle and gracious means of Salvation; Fear, Sorrow, Shame, Anguiſh and Dſepair, Wrack and Torment him: the Senſe of an Offended God, His Love and Mercy Deſpis'd, His Juſtice and Anger Provok'd; no length of Time, no change of Place, can give him any Eaſe: This is excellently Deſcrib'd in that dreadful
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93258:9"/>threat. (Deut. 23, 65. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>Thou ſhalt find no Eaſe, neither ſhall the ſole of thy foot have reſt; but the Lord ſhall give thee trembling of Heart, and failing of Eyes, and ſorrow of Mind, and thy life ſhall hang in Doubt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee; and thou ſhalt fear day and night: in the morning thou ſhalt ſay would God it were evening, and in the evening, thou ſhalt ſay would God it were morning.</hi> So reſtleſs a Condition, ſo far from any the leaſt Peace is the wicked Man. And this is the fartheſt from Remedy of any Evil, for other Afflictions Reaſon Cures, but Reaſon itſelf promotes remorſe upon ill Actions; gnawing upon the Soul to its Shame and Confuſion: For as they who have Agues or Fevers feel a more intenſe Heat or Cold than thoſe who dwell under the Pole or the Equinoctial: ſo the mind is leſs affected with outward Accidents; but an ill Conſcience! when 'tis Eccho'd from within, I! none but I my ſelf have been the cauſe of all this! what Torture and Deſpair! Whereas on the contrary, the worker of Righteouſneſs not only enjoys the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Pleaſure of his good Actions, but provides wiſely againſt Age, Adverſity, and Death itſelf, and lays up continually Satisfaction for Hereafter: Such Satisfaction as not only Reaſon promotes, but Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation Encourages by repeated Promiſes of the greateſt Aſſiſtance and Reward: Wherefore no Plenty of Riches, no Nobility of Blood, no Extent of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire can yield ſuch Serenity and Calmneſs to Life as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93258:10"/>the Souls being free from ill Actions; for when that Fountain of Action is preſerv'd pure and clear; good Deeds perpetually flowing from it, bleſs us with the ſweeteſt Peace, and fulleſt Happineſs; make us look back upon Life with Pleaſure, and forward upon Death with Joy. Let us then be ſo far from doubting of the Torments hereafter, or queſtioning the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of them, as rather to be Aſtoniſh'd at the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine goodneſs in promiſing Immortal Joys, Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Happineſs for our momentary Obedience here, when we have ſo great, and ſo immediate a Reward as a good Conſcience!</p>
            <p>But tho this may be ſo; yet, Can no outward Evils diſturb this Peace of the Mind? Will not the Malice of wicked Men, or the ſuddenneſs of great Afflictions ſhake and diſturb it? In anſwer to this I proceed to the other part of my Text, <hi>The effect of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Quietneſs and Aſſurance for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the firſt of theſe is meant that the Work of Righteouſneſs ſhall produce Peace in regard of our Neighbour: this we are aſſured from the Scriptures, <hi>That when a mans ways Pleaſe the Lord, he maketh his enemies to be at peace with him.</hi> (Prov. xvi. 7.) And that this is agreeable to Reaſon, will appear, if we conſider what it is that is moſt apt to Provoke or Pleaſe mankind, and the Nature of Goodneſs or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93258:10"/>Righteouſneſs in general. The great cauſe of Striſe and Contention is the Injuſtice that is offer'd to Men in their Perſons, Eſtates or Reputations, and that by Ambition, Covetouſneſs or Detraction: Ambition is generally the cauſe of the other two, for this being the thirſt of Power; Power conſiſts in the having many others at Command, and that comes to paſs either by their neceſſary Dependance upon us for their Intereſt, or their voluntary Service for Reward, and this is the Power of Riches; or elſe it conſiſts in the Reverence and Love which Men bear to Superior me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and this is the Power of Reputation. Both theſe Ambition endeavours to leſſen in others, and Uſurp for it ſelf by all kinds of Fraud and Injuſtice; and from the ſtriving for theſe on the one ſide, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to keep 'em on the other, ariſe moſt Quarrels and Diviſions: But the worker of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs makes no Enemies by theſe ways, but is fair and open in all his Words and Actions; Impartial to Himſelf, and Juſt to his Neighbour. Beſides, that Love and Charity which is every where inculcated in the Goſpel, ſo quiets our Paſſions, ſo ſoftens our Tempers, cauſes ſuch a generous neglect of Injuries, ſuch a ready and watchful diſpoſition to Oblige, ſuch a calmneſs and ſweetneſs of Converſation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Offence to the Preſent, or Injury to the Abſent;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93258:11"/>that a Righteous Man has no Affronts to Revenge, becauſe he gives none; and no Enemies to fear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he makes none: but on the contrary is lov'd and defended, becauſe he is a general Good, and becauſe his Peace and Happineſs is every Mans Intereſt.</p>
            <p>But further: this is ſo thro the nature of Goodneſs, or Righteouſneſs in general, which uſes of it ſelf either to prevail upon the beſt Tempers, or to Awe the Worſt.</p>
            <p>The Soul beeing moſt work'd upon by Senſible Objects, the power of Example is very Great in the doing Good as well as Evil. There is a Secret man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Conviction in good Actions, which perſuades more than all the force of Reaſon or Charms of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Something in Human Nature riſes and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes it ſelf againſt Arguments, eſpecially when they come from an Equal, not but that we could be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to entertain Truth could we find it out our ſelves; but we can ſeldom endure that Superiority which the Diſcovery of it ſeems to give others over us, no not in matters of the greateſt importance, of Salvation it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93258:11"/>
            <p> But when the light of our good Actions ſhines before Men, it pleaſes without ſuſpition; it wins in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly upon their Souls, and makes 'em to <hi>Glorifie,</hi> with us, <hi>our Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if Righteouſneſs has not this effect upon ſtubborn Minds, yet it ſtrikes 'em at leaſt with awe and terrour. The moſt ignorant People have very Early Notions of Good and Evil, and if theſe be any thing improv'd by Education, open'd and confirm'd by Reaſoning, 'tis impoſſible that they ſhould be ſo entirely rooted out by any Habit of Vice, but that there muſt remain enough of the Knowledge of Good to apprehend what is ſo in others, and regard it accordingly. There are many Inſtances in Hiſtory how Robbers and Murtherers have ſuddenly held their Hands at the ſight of ſingle and diſarm'd Men of known Goodneſs; and how raging Multitudes have been reſtrain'd by the Preſence of Men of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worth, as if, as S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays of <hi>Daniels</hi> Lions, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>T.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 17.) they ſaw the Venerable and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick Image of God Reſplendent in him, they beheld the ſame Characters of Goodneſs which were viſible in Adam before his Fall, when every Beaſt approach'd to receive its name from him; and this has been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93258:12"/>Obſervable in good Magiſtrates, or great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>who ſcatter evil with their Eyes,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly; their very looks being ſufficient to damp and chill the moſt ſucceſsful Impudence, and Habitual Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>But Laſtly, Tho this ſhould not be always ſo, but good Men may ſometimes ſuffer under the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of evil Men: and not only ſo; but tho they may be afflicted with any other Calamity whatſoever, yet the Work of Righteouſneſs is a ſufficient defence againſt this, in that Aſſurance which it always car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with it. This conſiſts in an Abſolute Truſt in God upon account of his Goodneſs, Wiſdom, and Power, and in a joyful Reſignation of our ſelves to his good Pleaſure; this is the effect of Righteouſneſs as 'tis the product of a good Conſcience. <hi>Beloved, if our Hearts Condemn us not,</hi> ſays S. <hi>John, then have we Confidence towards God;</hi> therefore no Affliction can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the Peace or Quiet of the Righteous; keep thy Eye fix'd in humble Confidence upon the God of Peace and nothing ſhall offend thee: <hi>Thou wilt keep him in perfect Peace whoſe mind is ſtaid on thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he truſted in thee.</hi> (Iſaiah xxvi. 3.) And what is the ground of this Aſſurance; the knowing that God will not tempt 'em; try 'em; farther then they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93258:12"/>are able to bear, and the ſhortneſs of ſuch Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als: we no ſooner hear <hi>that many are the Troubles of the Righteous, (Pſalm</hi> xxxiv. 19.) but it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows immediately, <hi>The Lord will deliver him out of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then again, the Prophet adds <hi>for ever:</hi> the Effect of Righteouſneſs ſhall be quiet, and Aſſurance for ever. This is that which makes the Righteous Mans Joy complete, and which ſettleth his Hope, and confirms his Faith; all other Aſſurance is vain and finite, that, in God infinite as His Being: What Confidence, alas! in Man, <hi>whoſe Days are a Shadow that flyeth away, their Breath goeth forth, they return to Earth, and all their Thoughts, their Projects periſh:</hi> This is the end of that buſie Creature, who is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious in Diſturbing his Neighbour and himſelf. <hi>But thou, O God, art from Everlaſting, and thy Years ſhall not fail; thou art God bleſſed for ever, and thy Righteouſneſs extends to Childrens Children, even to all Generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that Aſſurance for ever, which ſupports ſuch as work Righteouſneſs in the Day of Trouble, and in the Day of Death: All Evils are dreadful
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93258:13"/>only as they threaten Death; but what is this, in all its utmoſt Horror, to a good Conſcience? They who believe that all things happen by Chance, and that nothing is after Death, may be frighted and alarm'd at whatever diſturbs or ſhortens their <hi>only</hi> Being. But they who believe another World, may enjoy the fulleſt Quiet in the greateſt Afflictions, yes, when the blackeſt Calamities thicken dreadfully up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; this ſweet Aſſurance breaks thro all, and ſhews us beyond 'em the Proſpect of Heaven open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill wider and wider to our view, and the Son of God Himſelf encouraging us to be faithful unto Death (but unto Death, which is never far off in Proſperity, but which is ſtill nearer, the greater the Adverſity is) <hi>Be thou faithful unto Death, and I will give thee a Crown of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore with what an equal and deliberate Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, with what a generous Indifferency, as to Life or Death, doth the Good Chriſtian bear himſelf; he diſdains to fly to a Grave in the greateſt Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites; and yet whenever his Lord calls, he readily reſigns his Duſt and Aſhes; He gladly quits that Body which is ſubject to ſo many Dangers and Diſeaſes, to receive it again in a ſhort time; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it ſo chang'd, ſo improv'd, ſo ſpiritualiz'd, as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93258:13"/>never to be ſick, never to be tempted, never to be laid down more, but to remain with Him for ever, <hi>who is the firſt and the laſt, who liveth and was dead, and is now alive for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93258:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93258:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
